<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="-1809982591" Content_Hash="-74006671">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>03909259-9354-4b69-a27e-6419d05ef7ab</Id>
    <Library_Id>4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16</Library_Id>
    <Title>IISLockdown Tool Has Been Run on the Server</Title>
    <Category>Server Hardening</Category>
    <Phase>Deployment</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink />
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority>J.D. Meier, Alex Mackman, Michael Dunner, Srinath Vasireddy, Ray Escamilla and Anandha Murukan</Priority>
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[
<h1>Applies to</h1>
<ul>
<li>
<div>Web Application</div>
</li></ul>
<h1>What to Check For</h1>
<p>Check to ensure that IISLockdown tool has been run on the server to reduce the vulnerability of the Web server.</p>
<br>
<h1>How to Fix</h1>
<p>IISLockdown is available as an Internet download from the Microsoft Web site at
<a href="http://download.microsoft.com/download/iis50/utility/2.1/nt45xp/en-us/iislockd.exe">
http://download.microsoft.com/download/iis50/Utility/2.1/NT45XP/EN-US/iislockd.exe</a>.</p>
<p>Save IISlockd.exe in a local folder. IISlockd.exe is the IISLockdown wizard and not an installation program. You can reverse any changes made by IISLockdown by running IISlockd.exe a second time.</p>
<p>If you are locking down a Windows&nbsp;2000-based computer that hosts ASP.NET pages, select the Dynamic Web server template when the IISLockdown tool prompts you. When you select Dynamic Web server, IISLockdown does the following:
</p>
<ul>
<li>It disables the following insecure Internet services:
<ul>
<li>File Transfer Protocol (FTP) </li><li>E-mail service (SMTP) </li><li>News service (NNTP) </li></ul>
</li><li>It disables script mappings by mapping the following file extensions to the 404.dll:
<ul>
<li>Index Server </li><li>Web Interface (.idq, .htw, .ida) </li><li>Server-side include files (.shtml, .shtm, .stm) </li><li>Internet Data Connector (.idc) </li><li>.HTR scripting (.htr), Internet printing (.printer) </li></ul>
</li><li>It removes the following virtual directories: IIS Samples, MSADC, IISHelp, Scripts, and IISAdmin.
</li><li>It restricts anonymous access to system utilities as well as the ability to write to Web content directories using Web permissions.
</li><li>It disables Web Distributed Authoring and Versioning (WebDAV). </li><li>It installs the URLScan ISAPI filter. </li></ul>
<blockquote><strong><strong>Note</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</strong>If you are not using classic ASP, do not use the static Web server template. This template removes basic functionality that ASP.NET pages need, such as support for the
<strong>POST</strong> command.</blockquote>
<hr>
<p>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance.</p>
]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>