<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="1474736134" Content_Hash="993069648">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>43bbe2c2-3ab0-49b1-8740-88cb64357933</Id>
    <Library_Id>4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16</Library_Id>
    <Title>Null Sessions (Anonymous Logons) Are Disabled</Title>
    <Category>Server Hardening</Category>
    <Phase>Deployment</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink />
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority>J.D. Meier, Alex Mackman, Michael Dunner, Srinath Vasireddy, Ray Escamilla and Anandha Murukan</Priority>
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[
<h1>Applies to</h1>
<ul>
<li>
<div>Web Application</div>
</li></ul>
<h1>What to Check For</h1>
<p>Check to ensure that null sessions&nbsp;are disabled to prevent an attacker connecting to&nbsp;your server anonymously (without being authenticated).</p>
<br>
<h1>How to Fix</h1>
<p>To prevent anonymous access, disable null sessions. These are unauthenticated or anonymous sessions established between two computers. Unless null sessions are disabled, an attacker can connect to your server anonymously (without being authenticated).</p>
<p>Once an attacker establishes a null session, he or she can perform a variety of attacks, including enumeration techniques used to collect system-related information from the target computer — information that can greatly assist subsequent attacks. The type
 of information that can be returned over a null session includes domain and trust details, shares, user information (including groups and user rights), registry keys, and more.</p>
<p>Restrict Null sessions by setting <strong>RestrictAnonymous</strong> to <strong>
1</strong> in the registry at the following subkey:</p>
<p><strong>HKLM\System\CurrentControlSet\Control\LSA\RestrictAnonymous=1</strong></p>
<h1>Additional Resources</h1>
<ul>
<li>For more information, see Microsoft Knowledge Base article 246261, &quot;How To: Use the RestrictAnonymous Registry Value in Windows 2000.&quot; at
<a href="http://support.microsoft.com/kb/246261">http://support.microsoft.com/kb/246261</a></li></ul>
<p><strong></strong>&nbsp;</p>
<hr>
<p>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance.</p>
]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>