<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="-101053195" Content_Hash="669189900">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>5d43edf0-13de-45c6-b5a0-571049d53469</Id>
    <Library_Id>4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16</Library_Id>
    <Title>HTTP Requests Are Filtered. URLScan Is Installed And Configured</Title>
    <Category>Server Hardening</Category>
    <Phase>Deployment</Phase>
    <Technology> Any</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink />
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority>J.D. Meier, Alex Mackman, Michael Dunner, Srinath Vasireddy, Ray Escamilla and Anandha Murukan</Priority>
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[
<h1>Applies to</h1>
<ul>
<li>
<div>Web Application</div>
</li></ul>
<h1>What to Check For</h1>
<p>Check to ensure that URLScan is installed and configured so that all HTTP requests are filtered.</p>
<br>
<h1>How to Fix</h1>
<p>URLScan is installed when you run IISLockdown, although you can download it and install it separately.</p>
<blockquote><strong>Note</strong>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;IIS 6.0 on Windows Server 2003 has functionality equivalent to URLScan built in. Your decision whether to install UrlScan should be based on your specific organizational requirements. For more information, see &quot;<a href="http://www.microsoft.com/technet/security/tools/urlscan.mspx#eeaa">Installing
 UrlScan 2.5</a>.&quot;</blockquote>
<p><strong>To install URLScan without running IISLockdown</strong> </p>
<ol>
<li>Download IISlockd.exe from <a href="http://download.microsoft.com/download/iis50/utility/2.1/nt45xp/en-us/iislockd.exe">
http://download.microsoft.com/download/iis50/Utility/2.1/NT45XP/EN-US/iislockd.exe</a>.
</li><li>Run the following command to extract the URLScan setup:
<p>i<strong>islockd.exe /q /c</strong> </p>
</li></ol>
<p>URLScan blocks requests that contain unsafe characters (for example, characters that have been used to exploit vulnerabilities, such as &quot;..&quot; used for directory traversal). URLScan logs requests that contain these characters in the %windir%\system32\inetsrv\urlscan
 directory.</p>
<p>You configure URLScan using settings in the .ini file %windir%\system32\inetsrv\urlscan\urlscan.ini.</p>
<p>In addition to blocking malicious requests, you can use URLScan to defend your server against denial of service attacks before the requests reach ASP.NET. To do this, set limits in the
<strong>MaxAllowedContentLength</strong>, <strong>MaxUrl</strong>, and <strong>MaxQueryString</strong> arguments in the URLScan.ini file. For more information, see &quot;<a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa302368.aspx">How To: Use&nbsp;URLScan</a>&quot; in
 the &quot;How To&quot; section of this guide.</p>
<h3>Reversing URLScan Changes</h3>
<p>There is no automatic operation to remove URLScan. If you have problems with URLScan, you can either remove it from IIS or you can analyze the problem by logging requests that are rejected. To do this, use the option
<strong>RejectResponseUrl=/~*</strong> in the URLScan .ini file.</p>
<p>For more information about how to remove ISAPI filters, see &quot;<a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa302432.aspx#c16618429_021">Step 13. ISAPI Filters</a>,&quot; later in this chapter.</p>
<h1>Additional Resources</h1>
<p>See the following articles for more information about the URLScan tool: </p>
<ul>
<li>For information on running URLScan, see &quot;<a href="http://msdn2.microsoft.com/en-us/library/aa302368.aspx">How To: Use&nbsp;URLScan</a>&quot; .
</li><li>For information about URLScan configuration and the URLScan.ini file settings, see Microsoft Knowledge Base article 326444, &quot;How To: Configure the URLScan Tool.&quot;
</li></ul>
<hr>
<p>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance.</p>
]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>