<?xml version="1.0"?>
<TeamMentor_Article Metadata_Hash="1680140889" Content_Hash="-653978655">
  <Metadata>
    <Id>aa4270d8-cebf-4d7b-8044-08713aaf5888</Id>
    <Library_Id>4738d445-bc9b-456c-8b35-a35057596c16</Library_Id>
    <Title>Optimize Pages That Use SSL</Title>
    <Category>Communication Security</Category>
    <Phase>Implementation</Phase>
    <Technology>ASP.NET 3.5</Technology>
    <Type>Checklist Item</Type>
    <DirectLink />
    <Tag />
    <Security_Demand />
    <Author />
    <Priority>2</Priority>
    <Status />
  </Metadata>
  <Content Sanitized="true" DataType="Html">
    <Data><![CDATA[<h1>What to Do</h1>
  <p>Use SSL only for pages that require it. </p>
  <h1>Why</h1>
  <p>Using SSL is expensive in terms of performance. </p>
  <h1>When</h1>
  <p>Use SSL for pages that contain or capture sensitive data, such as pages that accept credit card numbers and passwords. Use SSL only if the following conditions are true: </p>
  <ul>
    <li>You want to encrypt the page data. </li>
    <li>You want to guarantee that the server to which you send the data is the server that you expect. </li>
  </ul>
  <h1>How</h1>
  <p>For pages where you must use SSL, follow these guidelines: </p>
  <ul>
    <li>Make the page size as small as possible. </li>
    <li>Avoid using graphics that have large file sizes. If you use graphics, use graphics that have smaller file sizes and resolution. Or, use graphics from a site that is not secure. However, when you use graphics from a site that is not secure, Web browsers display a dialog box that asks the user if the user wants to display the content from the site that is not secure. </li>
  </ul>
  <h1>Related Items</h1>
  <ul>
    <li>
      <a href="/article/834db5af-d3ce-4fe5-a546-7b5af56f840c">Use IPSsec to Encrypt Traffic Between Servers</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="/article/ce57bd55-7f7b-42b5-b7b0-59db156f2b94">Use SSL or IPSec for Secure Communication Between Entities</a>
    </li>
    <li>
      <a href="/article/c44d95ec-185a-4d3f-812b-4d3da3eb82a4">Use SSL Between the Web Browser and Web Server When Pages Need to be Encrypted<br /></a>
    </li>
  </ul>
  <hr />
  <p>Adapted from Microsoft patterns &amp; practices guidance. </p>]]></Data>
  </Content>
</TeamMentor_Article>